Hopansh Gahlot

+91-8791864585 | hopanshgahlot@gmail.com | LinkedIn | GitHub | Portfolio

Summary

Full Stack Developer with over 3 years of experience in the FinTech and SaaS industry. Skilled in React with strong capabilities in Node.js and Flask for back-end development. Experienced in using technology to solve complex challenges and create user-friendly solutions.

Work experience

Software Engineer - Pegasystems (Hyderabad)

November 2024 – Present

• Developing and maintaining scalable enterprise-level applications using React and the Pegasystems low-code application platform.

Associate Software Engineer 2 - Highradius (Hyderabad)

January 2024 – November 2024

- Developed a Chat-based Data Visualization & Support application using React and OpenAI
- Integrated **Retrieval augmented generation (RAG)** utility and **real-time chat functionality** with chatbot, reducing ticket volume by 30%

Associate Software Engineer 1 - Highradius (Hyderabad)

July 2022 - January 2024

- Enhanced the **Apache Superset** data visualization app by adding new charts with the help of **Echarts library**, increasing the variety of visualization components by 20%.
- Implemented **RESTful APIs** using **Flask**, facilitating integration between front-end and back-end systems.
- Engineered dashboard export and import functionalities, streamlining the creation process. This optimization eliminated 90% of redundant steps in dashboard development
- Wrote **Jest test suites**, leading to a 20% decrease in software defects and improved overall code quality.

Intern - Highradius (Bhubaneswar)

July 2021 – June 2022

- Contributed to 4+ web development projects using HTML, CSS, JavaScript, TypeScript, React, High-Charts, Material-UI and Node.js
- Gained experience with version control (git) and Agile methodologies
- Assisted in UI development for an AI-enabled B2B cloud application in the financial sector

Education

• Bachelors of Technology in Information Technology, Kalinga Institute of Industrial Technology, Bhubaneswar (2018 – 2022)

Skills

| Frontend | HTML, CSS, JavaScript. TypeScript. React, Material UI, Ant Design |
|----------|---|
| Backend | NodeJS, Python, Flask |
| Database | MySQL, MongoDB |
| DevOps | Docker, Git, GitHub Actions, Google Cloud Program |
| Testing | Jest, React Testing Library |

Projects

- ACADMIK: LLM-driven quiz and note creator built with React and Flask, leveraging the llama3-8B model.
- GIGGLE MATRIX: React app with Open-AI powered reverse image search using vector database.
- CHAT2CHART: Web app for creating charts from text prompts using React, Flask, and OpenAI.
- ED. ADDRESS: MERN stack web app for posting and finding tutoring services.
- CSS ARITH: TypeScript NPM library for arithmetic operations on CSS units

Achievements & Interests

- Intern of the Quarter: Q3 2021, Q2 2022
- Employee of the Quarter: Q2 2023
- Led a front-end development team on a high-impact project, ensuring successful delivery
- Enjoy portrait photography and digital art as hobbies